computer hello Freddy of thank you so
much for making time this has been I've
been looking forward to this all day for
me this is a really special moment it's
really nice to talk to you again
we've had some stimulating conversations
in the past both personally and done on
video and so I really look forward to
that great so I've prepared a couple of
questions for you and I always like to
give people an opportunity to start a
little bit from their story and your
story is so fascinating because um you
started your professional career very
successfully as physicist the research
physicist worked in a number of really
well
renown institutions as a physicist and
then somehow something happened that
made you look at life as a planetary
process and ecology and biology in much
more detail so I would love to take us
on a journey for you to take us on a
journey to tell what made that change
it's it's actually a long journey and
and I have to try and sort of summarize
it and it all began in the 1960s this
was a period in which I experienced a
profound personal transformation
these were my formative years I was in
my twenties I you know I I graduated in
physics and at the University of Vienna
in in 65 and then had my first postdoc
appointments and I was very much
influenced by the cultural movements of
the 1960s and looking back now I can say
that there were two main cultural
movements and both of them had to do
with an expansion of consciousness an
expansion of consciousness in two
different directions into the spiritual
dimension of consciousness and into the
social dimension
so in the spiritual dimension you had a
very strong interest in meditation in
Eastern spirituality in indigenous
spirituality with the books of Castaneda
for example and this was supported by
the arts by music by literature there
was this famous book Hundred Years of
Solitude
by Garcia Marquez the magic realism that
was really very characteristic of the
60s and of course there was
experimentation with psychedelics so all
of that combined to a very strong
expansion of consciousness into the
spirit spiritual domain and then there
was the social consciousness raising as
it was called in those days and that I
see essentially as a very broad
questioning of authority so we had the
civil rights movement in the United
States questioning the authority of
whites over blacks we had the women's
movement questioning patriarchal
Authority the student movements
questioning the authority of teachers
and university administrators the Prague
Spring and the Dubcek questioning the
authority of the Soviet regime and again
this was supported by the arts the films
of Anthony Fellini Goethe and so on
theater played a big role the living
theater for example so I was very much
influenced by all that and in the 1970s
I first went into the spiritual
dimension in my work exploring parallels
between modern physics and Eastern
spirituality in my first book the tower
physics published in 1975
then I went into the social and
ecological direction with my second book
the turning point published in 1982
where I explored this paradigm shift
that had happened in physics from a
mechanistic world view to a holistic or
ecological view and I explored it in
various areas and and examined various
issues such as healthcare management the
economy cycle psychology and
psychotherapy and so on and somewhere in
the late sometime between the late 70s
and early 80s I realized that all these
problems had to do with life actually I
realized it under the influence of
Gregory Bateson with whom I spent a lot
of time in 1981 and 82 80 81 82 and so I
realized that all sorry was that and I
also went there to do to give seminars
and so I had long discussions with
Bateson and so I realized that these
issues all had to do with living systems
with individual organisms social systems
and ecosystems and so my focus shifted
from physics to the life sciences
because physics although it's relevant
but it really can't tell you anything
about the essential nature of life so
that's what I became interested in and
then for the next thirty years I put
together a synthesis of an emerging new
conception of life in terms of networks
in terms of patterns in terms of
relationships and already in my book the
turning point I called this
the systems for your flight and at the
end of this trajectory is a textbook
that I wrote with my friend and
colleague Pierluigi Luisi biochemist at
the University of Rome and we called it
the system's view of life and this is
for me my grand synthesis of this new
conception of life which integrates four
dimensions of life the biological
dimension obviously but also the
cognitive dimension the social dimension
and the ecological dimension so that's a
long trajectory from the sixties when I
got my inspiration to the 1970s when you
know some conceptual framework began to
emerge to the 80s where I got involved
in green politics and and just went on
and on and having really lived so
intimately with some of the the pioneers
as well I mean you know so many of the
the early actors in the environmental
movement who really raised awareness
about the global situation and these
converging crisises as you've called
them yourself and having seen all the
Big Easy what you just said there that
in the 1960s and even early 1970s this
social change in environmental change
movement was very much also accompanied
by cultural change by the arts theater
music all of that right now
there seems to be another upsurge of
issues or like that but we still haven't
reached that broad social movement that
includes the arts and culture enough and
having already lived through it 50 years
ago are you hopeful that this time
around we see a lot looking back I feel
now that social change
of course does not happen as smoothly
it's not you know a broad trajectory
toward a different society different
economics different culture I came to
see more like a pendulum but not a
regular pendulum a chaotic pendulum this
is something we study in chaos theory
this this is a pendulum that is highly
irregular unpredictable and goes back
and forth but never in the same way and
so we had the early inspiration the
change of awareness in the 1960s and
1970s we had the political manifestation
in green politics and in the 1980s and I
believed to what the end of the 1980s
that we were now ready to embrace this
new vision of reality and embodied
politically and really changed the world
well what happened then was something
totally unforeseen which nobody had
predicted and that was the information
technology revolution which led among
many other things to a new a new
materialism really and of course a new
global economy which was dominated by
and wasit is dominated by corporations
and brought with it
materialism and greed very much the
opposite of the values we had developed
in the 60s and 70s and it took us a
whole decade the decade of the 90s to
really deal with that because
globalization that was the sort of
umbrella term is not only economic
globalization corporate economic
globalization but also cultural
globalization you and I today we and and
even more so younger people lives in in
a networked world in a globally
work well and so we were very excited
about that but the shadow side is the
the corporate economy which is you know
geared toward exploitation and about
shifting wealth from you know as the
Occupy movements at the 99% to to the 1%
so in 1999 there was the meeting of the
WTO the World Trade Organization in
Seattle where a new global civil society
emerged and and so now we have two main
forces we have the corporate world the
corporate economy and we have the global
civil society and they are on a
collision course and and the crisis that
I described and foresaw in the turning
point in in the late 70s has now
intensified and of course it has been
exacerbated by climate change really
climate breakdown which we also foresaw
you know I wrote about climate change or
global warming as as it was called then
in 1988 so that's that's a long time ago
but and of course we could have
alleviated it much easier than we can
now so there is there is a sharp crisis
well am i hopeful I am hopeful yes but
in a particular sense I have been very
much inspired by BATS love hobble I met
Hubble in 1997 when he invited me to a
symposium called forum 2000 and I was
I've been very much inspired by
something he wrote when he was a
dissident and was actually in prison and
it is a meditation on hope where Hubble
sees hope as he says as a dimension of
the soul and not as the result of
assessment of the situation in the world
let me read to you what what he writes
hope is not the conviction that
something will turn out well but the
certainty that something makes sense
regardless of how it turns out and so
I've tried to live like that I've been
very inspired by that ya know that's
really rings true the how do you see
I mean you rightly spoke to that the
many faceted dimensions of that
globalization process that neoliberal
globalization had took took hold of us
in the 1990s and one of them is like a
globalization or colonialization of the
mind which has been going on for a long
time it's it's and we need to re-educate
and begin to see the world from a
systems pure view of life and there's
still so few institutions in the world
that actually really focus on that
education that is now so neat I mean you
co founded the Center for eco literacy
and and spent a long time actually
looking at how how do we start through
education to create this mind shift and
and we first met at Omaha College in
2001 and I would love to take to take
this opportunity for you to say a little
bit about you've had a relationship with
Juma has since the beginning and why do
you think because in those days that was
the only place you taught regularly yes
and could you say a little bit more
about what you first let me say that it
is true that systems thinking and the
the ecological values the values of deep
ecology which are essentially spiritual
values all that all that is not in the
mainstream however it is very broadly
embraced in the global civil society
which is very powerful and it has
hundreds and hundreds of NGOs with their
research institutes and centers of
learning where this thinking is is
developed and practiced
and trauma Hawk college for the last
what is it thirty forty years has been
at the forefront it is a very unique
center of transformative learning
learning where you not only absorb ideas
in information but where you really
transform in your your very nature and
as you know it was founded by our friend
and mentor Satish Kumar who thought and
I discussed this with him several times
that this transformative learning would
best take place in community in locally
rooted community although rooted there
only for a short time but he has been
able to create a very strong sense of
community where people from all over the
world take short courses of two or three
weeks and not only learn together but
also live together and work together run
the college in terms of cooking cleaning
gardening and so on and so while they're
doing this they talk they talk around
the clock
they they they discuss things in the
lectures in the morning and then they
talk while they're cutting vegetables
they talk by they're preparing rooms for
special events and they end up late late
at night you know talking in the bar you
know tasting Scottish single malt
whiskey no edge of chaos and so so this
creates a very strong sense of community
and in particular in my courses when the
subject of learning is patterns of
relationships because that's what
systems thinking is all about and when
you experience patterns of human
relationships at the same time
that's very powerful and so that's why I
think Schumann college is so unique yeah
I mean I'm I'm a testimony for it
because basically it was your work and
some extent Joanna Macy's work in John
seats work that first made me aware of
the college and that made me want to go
there because I found out that all three
of you were occasionally teaching there
and then being there for 18 months in
between 2001 and 2003 really did exactly
what you just described the transform my
Leslie they have these longer courses
also the MSC program so that's what you
took right
okay I was on the masters and holistic
science and the but the fourth year of
it running and and then I stayed on as a
helper and part of the college community
for another half year after the course
yeah but since since so much has moved
on even then like I mean I think Satish
is absolutely right the most
transformative experience embodied
learning experience happens in community
I mean even the Buddha said that one of
the columns of Buddhism is the Sangha
the community but but now these these
days because we're such a globally
interconnected human community around
the planet and online learning is
something that while at the beginning we
might have looked at it not as ideal or
not as powerful as face-to-face learning
we've realized that can do wonderful
things and you yourself have set up a
wonderful online course that I've also
had the pleasure not to take twice
already the fridge of couple of course
and I also think it created a really
nice schedule for it but not only has it
been a very well received course you
have grown it into a community of global
graduates from that's really interesting
can you tell about that story the
subject of my course which is called you
know officially you know the system's
view of life but for PR purposes Capra
cost because it's easy to remember and
it has a website Capra course taught net
and so it is based on the textbook that
I wrote with Luigi the four dimensions
of the system's view of life integrating
the biological the cognitive the social
and the ecological and it consists of
twelve pre-recorded lectures of about 40
minutes and they were recorded for some
reason in Brazil in the home of an
architect a beautiful living room with a
very small group of participants and I
can tell you I don't know whether you
realize this watching the lectures that
this is really modeled after Samaha
college because when you see people
sitting on the floor and on couches in
this sort of intimate environment
discussing things that's what I've done
with people at Yuma College for twenty
years and so I modeled my lectures after
that and in addition to the lectures
there is a discussion forum an online
discussion forum where people post
comments and questions and I participate
in that during the whole course
so for 12 weeks one lecture a week I'm
there every day for about half an hour
to an hour answering questions and and
that has been a real experience for me
because although I don't have the face
to face contact with people that I have
in a classroom the conversations and the
discussions are much more substantial
because in a classroom when you teach in
a classroom and somebody asks you a
question you have to say something you
have to answer whether you know that an
answer or not you have to say something
online that's not true I can go away and
do some research I can look at books I
can I can browse the internet that can
think about it and usually what I do in
the morning when I brush my teeth during
the course and and shave I think
but I checked the questioners first when
I get up and then I think about it and
Mull them over and then I go and discuss
things with my students so as you
mentioned the course is now run for four
years we have thirteen hundred more or
less alumni around the world in almost I
think in 70 countries now on all
continents and even in a single course
you know the next course is starting on
let me see the 26th of February and have
these postcards and we have over a
hundred registrations now for the 26th
of February from about 30 countries
around the world from all continents so
like at Omaha college it's this
multicultural you know global community
and we have so many alumni now that we
have alumni meetings on zoom' like you
and I have right now but also face to
face because whenever I travel somewhere
I meet alumni where they go to Italy or
to Austria or to London or to Sweden I
have alumni meetings and and I don't
need to be there they have alumni
meetings in in Rio de Janeiro and in
when Osiris and in various places around
the world so I'm really realizing my
dream here to grow a global community a
global network of systemic thinkers and
activists and it's very fulfilling to me
it's for me and this is so wonderful and
I'm gonna in a minute stop this and then
we'd go into the second part and but one
thing that I learned from our common
friend Brian Goodwin while at you know
her college is that you can't really
predict and control complex dynamic
systems but the one way of influencing
emergence in a way that it is more
likely to be positive properties that
emerge rather than negative ones is to
pay attention to who's connected to whom
in the system
and what the quality of the connections
and also what information flows in the
system and the quality of the
information and what I hear you doing
with this course is actually building a
network of global systems thinkers that
that I imbued and understand the
system's view of life because they had
the privilege of learning directly from
you and and then engaging them with each
other and so much beautiful things can
happen from that yeah and also it it
underlying it all is a system of shared
values and a certain spiritual attitude
which is implicit and this is also
something I learned from Satish Kumar at
Summa College
Satish who is a spiritual teacher does
not push Jainism or Hinduism or or any
religion
he doesn't even push meditation you know
when he comes to the college as you will
remember what he does he goes to the
kitchen and he cooks with students so so
it's a very it's a in fact a Gandhian
type of spirituality and and so in the
Capra cause also there is a very strong
connection which I think is partly you
know it's an emotional and partly
spiritual connection no I completely
agree I mean it's a teach himself gave
me this beautiful image of saying it
doesn't really matter you can em ecology
like the ecological view of life the
system's view of life and spirituality
are really sides of the same coin
you can go in to enter the door of
spirituality and if you really go deep
about interbeing and interconnection
with life you end up learning about
ecology and the other option is you go
in as a scientist and you go deep into
ecology and the systemic interconnection
and a complex dynamic system that is
constantly transforming and suddenly you
have insights that are deeply spiritual
insights and of course you know as a
systems thinker I would say since
everything is interconnected it doesn't
matter where you start
wonderful let's stop here and we just
immediately go for the for the next